    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>JSXGraph<footnote><para><ulink url="http://jsxgraph.org">http://jsxgraph.org</ulink></para>
                </footnote>  
            is a client-side web application/library for advanced visualizations in a web browser. Its range of application starts from
            the display of simple bar and pie charts to the interactive display of function graphs and Geometry constructions knwon from the good old
            Highschool days. 
            Even more advanced features of JSXGraph are the on-the-fly solving of Differential Equation Systems, the display of 
            Lindenmayer systems<footnote><para>Inspired by the work of Sam Ruby: <ulink url="http://intertwingly.net/blog/2006/07/06/Penrose-Tiling">http://intertwingly.net/blog/2006/07/06/Penrose-Tiling</ulink></para>
            </footnote>, which are of importance in Biology, and dynamic computation of regression polynomials.
        </para>
        <para>
            JSXGraph is a library which may be used in various situations. The main application is to be some kind of a viewer applet for
            educational Mathematics material from schools and universities. 
            Many of these constructions, especially from Euclidean Geometry, are available in some propietary XML file format. Usually they are 
            displayed by some Java applet. In order to compensate the slow demise of Java applets in the web browsers, JSXGraph may prove to be
            useful. At the moment JSXGraph supports the file format of 
            GEONExT<footnote><para><ulink url="http://geonext.de">http://geonext.de</ulink></para></footnote>, 
            Intergeo<footnote><para><ulink url="http://i2geo.net">http://i2geo.net</ulink></para></footnote>, 
            and - at least partially - 
            GeoGebra<footnote><para><ulink url="http://geogebra.org">http://geogebra.org</ulink></para></footnote>.
        </para>
        <para>
            Beside the usage as viewer of existing material, the JSXGraph library may be used as an API for advanced special purpose visualizations.
            JSXGraph enables interactive experiments with sophisticated mathematical models, for example the 
            epidemiology model of the swine flu<footnote><para><ulink url="http://jsxgraph.uni-bayreuth.de/wiki/index.php/SIR_model:_swine_flu">http://jsxgraph.uni-bayreuth.de/wiki/index.php/SIR_model:_swine_flu</ulink></para></footnote>.
            The possibilities of JSXGraph in this respect exceed by far the options offered by software which is common in schools today.
        </para>
        <para>
            Another possible application of JSXGraph is as front end for server based applications. 
            One example is the popular free statistics software R<footnote><para><ulink url="http://jsxgraph.uni-bayreuth.de/wiki/index.php/Analyze_data_with_the_Statistics_software_R">http://jsxgraph.uni-bayreuth.de/wiki/index.php/Analyze_data_with_the_Statistics_software_R</ulink></para></footnote>. On the mouse up event
            data is sent via AJAX to R interface on server side. The result of the computation is sent back to the browser
            and displayed by JSXGraph. 
            JSXGraph can also be used on server side to generate charts - for example with PHP - which are sent to the 
            Browser. The download size of JSXGraph is less than 100 kByte, which is smaller than most bitmap images.
        </para>
        <para>
            From a technical point of view, JSXGraph is implemented in JavaScript. It generates SVG output on Mozilla- and Webkit-based 
            browsers, and VML on the Internet Explorer. 
            Therefore, JSXGraph runs on every modern browser. 
        </para>
        <para>
            JSXGraph is open source software, released under the LGPL – Lesser GNU General Public License. The source code
            is hosted by sourceforge.
        </para>
    </section>
