<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0b5//EN"
               "docbook_5.0b5.dtd" [
<!ENTITY chapter_introduction SYSTEM "chapter_introduction.xml" >
<!ENTITY chapter_server SYSTEM "chapter_server.xml" >
<!ENTITY chapter_plugins SYSTEM "chapter_plugins.xml" >
<!ENTITY chapter_implementation SYSTEM "chapter_implementation.xml" >
]>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Interactive SVG with JSXGraph</title>
        <subtitle>JSXGraph</subtitle>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>conference proceedings</keyword>
            <keyword>paper formats</keyword>
        </keywordset>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Bianca</firstname>
                    <surname>Valentin</surname>
                </personname>
                <email>bianca.valentin@uni-bayreuth.de</email>
                <personblurb><para>Bla bla</para></personblurb>
                <affiliation>
                    <jobtitle>PhD student</jobtitle>
                    <org>
                        <orgname>University of Bayreuth</orgname>
                        <orgdiv>Department of mathematics</orgdiv>
                        <address>
                            <city>Bayreuth</city>
                            <street>Universitaetsstr. 30</street>
                            <postcode>95444</postcode>
                            <country>Germany</country>
                            <phone>++49-921 55 3389</phone>
                        </address>   
                    </org>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Michael</firstname>
                    <surname>Gerhaeuser</surname>
                </personname>
                <email>michael.gerhaeuser@gmail.com</email>
                <personblurb><para>Bla bla</para></personblurb>
                <affiliation>
                    <jobtitle>Student</jobtitle>
                    <org>
                        <orgname>University of Bayreuth</orgname>
                        <orgdiv>Department of mathematics</orgdiv>
                        <address>
                            <city>Bayreuth</city>
                            <street>Universitaetsstr. 30</street>
                            <postcode>95444</postcode>
                            <country>Germany</country>
                            <phone></phone>
                        </address>   
                    </org>
                </affiliation>
            </author>            
        </authorgroup>
        <!-- If you have several authors, you could nest all authors within an authorgroup element -->
        <abstract>
            <para>JSXGraph is a client-side web library for displaying interactive mathematics and drawings in a web browser. This article shall demonstrate the possibilities of JSXGraph and explain how they are implemented.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    
    &chapter_introduction;        

    <section>
        <title>Mathematics</title>
        <para>The originally intended purpose of JSXGraph was having a JavaScript library for displaying geometric constructions in a web browser. So it is possible to visualize geometric elements that are taught in schools and universities like points, lines, circles, arcs, and angles, as well as predefined composition elements. JSXGraph not only provides tools for displaying geometric constructions but also for doing calculus like plotting curves starting from function graphs with tangents up to parametric and polar curves, splines or other interpolation methods. </para>
        <section>
            <title>JSXGraph as a web viewer for dynamic geometry software</title>
            <para>Dynamic geometry software (DGS) are computer programs which allow one to create and then manipulate geometric constructions, primarily in plane geometry. In most DGS, one starts construction by putting a few points and using them to define new objects such as lines, circles or other points. After some construction is done, one can move the points one started with and see how the construction changes.</para>
            <para>
            There are lots of different available software packages to play around dynamically with geometry at schools and universities. Most of them are written in Java, such as GeoGebra, Cinderella, Compass and Ruler or GEONExT, others like The Geometer's Sketchpad or Cabri offer a Java based web viewer. So if you want to integrate a construction that was created with one of these DGS in a web page, it takes some time to load the corresponding Java applet before you can use it. There are moreover big doubts about the future of Java in a web browser because Java applets are vanishing more and more from the internet and are actually not supported in browsers on modern mobile internet devices. As a result, the idea of JSXGraph was to read GEONExT Files and display them in the browser using JavaScript to manage the corresponding DOM elements of SVG or VML, depending on what browser is used. JavaScript is furthermore used to realize the dynamic in DGS by capturing the browser's mouse events. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Currently supported file formats</title>
            <para>Since JSXGraph has evolved from the GEONExT project, the support of its file format is almost complete. 
Other file formats are under development. For example, JSXGraph is involved in the European Intergeo project which shall unite several dynamic geometry softwares (GeoGebra, Cabri, GEONExT, Cinderella, etc.) agreeing about a common file format that can be displayed within a browser using the Intergeo reader of JSXGraph. Support for reading GeoGebra files directly is under development in cooperation with the GeoGebra developers.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Constructing from scratch</title>
            <para>The JSXGraph API used in the readers for the different file formats can also be used to create a construction from scratch or to manipulate a construction loaded from a given file. JSXGraph contains functions for compass and ruler constructions in euclidean geometry basing on points, lines, circles, arcs, and angles. Those can be intersected or combined in predefined ways. For example one can construct a line that is parallel to another one or a point that is the midpoint between two other points by using integrated JSXGraph methods. Additionally, one can easily implement own composition elements with JavaScript and the above-mentioned functions. 
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Calculus</title>
            <para>Beyond the capabilities of JSXGraph with regard to geometric constructions, one is also able to visualize calculus.</para>
            <para>The possibilities start from plotting simple functiongraphs to displaying more complex graphs like parametric and polar curves which can be analyzed using the implemented methods for tangents, integrals or spline interpolation. 
            </para>
            <para>Example:  examine the influence of function parameters like in code example 1[TODO]</para>
            <para>With an implementation of an explicit Runge-Kutta process, JSXGraph can also solve ordinary differential equations on the fly with the opportunity to change the parameters on runtime and watching the results.
            </para>
        </section>            
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Turtle graphics</title>
        <para>Turtle graphics as a method of drawing offer a huge variety of applications. So JSXGraph provides a comfortable support of functions round about them.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Turtle graphics in mathematical modelling</title>
            <para>Mathematic modelling with differential equations can also be done by using turtle graphics. Exponential population growth model can be easily simulated by using the discrete analogue of the corresponding differential equation and computing the movement of the turtle in equidistant small time intervals. </para>
                <programlisting><![CDATA[ 
                var board = JXG.JSXGraph.initBoard('box', {originX: 10, originY: 250, unitX: 40, unitY: 20, axis:true});
                var t = board.createElement('turtle',[4,3,70]);
                ...
                var dy = alpha*t.Y()*dx;   // Exponential growth
                t.moveTo([dx+t.X(),dy+t.Y()]);
                ]]></programlisting>
            <para>In a similar way, logistic or autocatalytic population growth processes can be modelled. A further application which can be simulated with turtle graphics is epidemiology where a set of differential equations is given to predict the immediate consequences of a epidemic like the Hong Kong flu or the swine flu. With few lines of programm code in JSXGraph one can study the chronological sequence of the rate of susceptible, infected and recovered population.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Drawing with turtle graphics</title>
            <para>An advantage of using turtle graphics is the easy way to draw. The standard commands are going forward for a given numer of units and turning left or right in a given angle. The following programm listing draws the Nikolaus graph shown in the picture below.</para>
                <programlisting><![CDATA[ 
                for(i=1;i<=4;i++) {
                    t.forward(100);
                    t.right(90);
                }
                t.right(45);
                t.forward(100*Math.sqrt(2));
                for(i=1;i<=2;i++) {
                   t.left(90);
                   t.forward(50*Math.sqrt(2));
                }
                t.left(90);
                t.forward(100*Math.sqrt(2));
            ]]></programlisting>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
                <figure xml:id="nikolaus">
                    <title>The Nikolaus Graph</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="nikolaus.svg" format="svg" width="60%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                         <textobject><phrase>The Nikolaus Graph</phrase></textobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            ]]></programlisting>       
            <para>This approach can be used to produce easily beautiful Lindenmayer systems known from chaos theory like plants or penrose tilings. Similarly, well-known fractals like the Sierpinski triangle or the Koch curve can be drawn. Other applications can be found in statistics where one can simulate random walks with turtles. Additionally, abecedarian games like snake can be implemented in a few lines.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Charts</title>
        <para>Having all the geometric objects with all their possibilities within JSXGraph, it was not difficult to integrate support for charts which provide all the optical properties that are integrated in JSXGraph. So it is possible to create easily dynamic bar charts or interactive pie charts.</para>
        <!--<para>
            JSXGraph uses the style properties that are offered by SVG and VML, so that the geometric objects can be displayed in different colors and styles that can be changed on runtime.</para>        -->
        <section>
            <title>Title of subsubsection</title>
            <para>A paragraph ...</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    &chapter_server;

    &chapter_plugins;
    
    &chapter_implementation;    
    
    
    <bibliography xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
        <bibliodiv><title>Books</title>
            <biblioentry xml:id="Crockford2008">
                <abbrev>Crockford2008</abbrev>
                <authorgroup>
                    <author><personname>
                        <firstname>Douglas.</firstname><surname>Crockford</surname>
                    </personname></author>
                </authorgroup>
                <biblioid class="isbn">978-0-596-51774-8</biblioid>
                <publisher>
                    <publishername>O'Reilly</publishername>
                </publisher>
                <title>JavvaScript: The Good Parts</title>
            </biblioentry>

            <biblioentry xml:id="VML98">
                <abbrev>VML1998</abbrev>
                <authorgroup>
                    <author><personname><firstname>John</firstname><surname>Bowler</surname></personname></author>
                    <author><personname><firstname>Howard</firstname><surname>Cooperstein</surname></personname></author>
                    <author><personname><firstname>Brian</firstname><surname>Dister</surname></personname></author>
                    <author><personname><firstname>Ajay</firstname><surname>Jindal</surname></personname></author>
                    <author><personname><firstname>Daniel</firstname><surname>Lee</surname></personname></author>
                    <author><personname><firstname>Brian</firstname><surname>Mathews</surname></personname></author>
                    <author><personname><firstname>Tuan</firstname><surname>Nguyen</surname></personname></author>
                    <author><personname><firstname>Troy</firstname><surname>Sandal</surname></personname></author>
                    <author><personname><firstname>Peter</firstname><surname>Wu</surname></personname></author>
                </authorgroup>
                <copyright><year>1998</year>
                    <holder>W3C</holder></copyright>
                <biblioid class="isbn"></biblioid>
                <publisher>
                    <publishername>http://www.w3.org/TR/1998/NOTE-VML-19980513</publishername>
                </publisher>
                <title>Vector Markup Language (VML)</title>
            </biblioentry>

            <!-- OLD -->
            
            <biblioentry xml:id="AhoSethiUllman96">
                <abbrev>AhoSethiUllman96</abbrev>
                <authorgroup>
                    <author><personname>
                        <firstname>Alfred V.</firstname><surname>Aho</surname>
                    </personname></author>
                    <author><personname>
                        <firstname>Ravi</firstname><surname>Sethi</surname>
                    </personname></author>
                    <author><personname>
                        <firstname>Jeffrey D.</firstname><surname>Ullman</surname>
                    </personname></author>
                </authorgroup>
                <copyright><year>1996</year>
                    <holder>Bell Telephone Laboratories, Inc.</holder></copyright>
                <editor><personname>
                    <firstname>James T.</firstname><surname>DeWolf</surname>
                </personname></editor>
                <biblioid class="isbn">0-201-10088-6</biblioid>
                <publisher>
                    <publishername>Addison-Wesley Publishing Company</publishername>
                </publisher>
                <title>Compilers, Principles, Techniques, and Tools</title>
            </biblioentry>
            
            <biblioentry xreflabel="Kites75">
                <authorgroup>
                    <author><personname>
                        <firstname>Andrea</firstname><surname>Bahadur</surname>
                    </personname></author>
                    <author><personname>
                        <firstname>Mark</firstname><surname>Shwarek</surname>
                    </personname></author>
                </authorgroup>
                <copyright><year>1974</year><year>1975</year>
                    <holder>Product Development International Holding N. V.</holder>
                </copyright>
                <biblioid class="isbn">0-88459-021-6</biblioid>
                <publisher>
                    <publishername>Plenary Publications International, Inc.</publishername>
                </publisher>
                <title>Kites</title>
                <subtitle>Ancient Craft to Modern Sport</subtitle>
                <pagenums>988-999</pagenums>
            </biblioentry>
            
        </bibliodiv>
        <bibliodiv><title>Periodicals</title>
            
            <biblioentry>
                <abbrev>Walsh97</abbrev>
                <biblioset relation="journal">
                    <title>XML: Principles, Tools, and Techniques</title>
                    <publisher>
                        <publishername>O'Reilly &amp; Associates, Inc.</publishername>
                    </publisher>
                    <biblioid class="issn">1085-2301</biblioid>
                    <editor><personname>
                        <firstname>Dan</firstname><surname>Connolly</surname>
                    </personname></editor>
                </biblioset>
                <biblioset relation="article">
                    <title>A Guide to XML</title>
                    <author><personname>
                        <surname>Walsh</surname><firstname>Norman</firstname>
                    </personname></author>
                    <copyright><year>1997</year><holder>ArborText, Inc.</holder></copyright>
                    <pagenums>97-108</pagenums>
                </biblioset>
            </biblioentry>
            
        </bibliodiv>
        
    </bibliography>
</article>
